Finding Aid for John D. Dingell Papers
Bentley Historical Library
John D. Dingell Papers
1932-1956
Bentley Historical Library
Dingell, John D. (John David), 1894-1955
861021 Aa/2
4 linear feet
Democratic congressman from Michigan's 15th District, 1933-1955, Dingell served on Ways and Means Committee beginning in his second term and was an ardent supporter of President Franklin D. Roosevelt and New Deal policies. He played a significant role in passage of the Social Security Act. Papers include correspondence, clippings, press releases, speeches and interviews.
The collection was donated by the Hon. John D. Dingell, Jr. on February 26, 1985. Donor no. 7161
The collection is open for research.
John D. Dingell was born in Detroit on February 2, 1894. He resided in the city for his entire life, except for a brief stay in Colorado Springs, where he met and married his wife, Grace. Dingell pursued various careers, including newspaper writer and wholesale meat broker, before being elected in 1932 to serve as U.S. Representative from Michigan's newly-created 15th District in Western Detroit. He served Detroit continuously as U.S. Representative until his death on September 19, 1955 (his seat has since that date been filled by his son, John D. Dingell).
Dingell was elected as a "wet" Democrat and was an ardent supporter of President Franklin D. Roosevelt and the New Deal. He was a member of the Ways and Means Committee from his second term. In the committee, Dingell helped to hammer out the Social Security Act. For the next twenty years he introduced bills to liberalize and extend Social Security benefits. Dingell was an outspoken and active spokesman for the employees of the Federal Government. His other legislative interests included the reduction or elimination of excise taxes; he also submitted numerous bills on trade issues, especially trade with Canada. He was one of the earliest and most consistent champions of the St. Lawrence Seaway project. From 1943 to his death, Dingell led the unsuccessful fight in the House for President Truman's national health insurance program.
Dingell was identified with most of the liberal Democratic issues of his day. He was, however, in advance of the bulk of his peers in working for anti-pollution laws, anti-lynch bills, and economic aid for Israel. Dingell also conscientiously pursued more mundane projects, such as new post offices, commemorative stamps for Detroit, and personal appeals from constituents.
The collection has been arranged into three series: Biographical; Speeches, Press Releases, and Interviews; Legislation.
The papers of John Dingell span the years 1932-1955. The papers appear to represent a portion of his congressional office file. The collection consists of correspondence (both incoming and outgoing) and clippings relating to many of the bills which Dingell introduced, and copies of press statements, speeches, and interviews. There is no personal material. There are no documents relating to his committee work or to legislation introduced by other members of the House. Nor do the files of his own bills seem complete (for instance, Dingell's anti-pollution bill is missing). By and large the correspondence is fairly routine or for public consumption. Some of the correspondence is from constituents, some from special interest groups, and some (though not much) from colleagues.
Civil service.; Courts -- Michigan.; Detroit (Mich.); United States -- Emigration and immigration.; Insurance -- United States.; Judges -- United States.; Alcoholic beverage industry.; New Deal, 1933-1939.; Saint Lawrence Seaway.; Tariff -- United States.; Taxation -- United States.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1929-1933.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1933-1953.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1953-1961.; Immigrants -- United States.; Democratic Party (U.S.); Dingell, John D. (John David), 1894-1955.; United States. Congress. House.
- Biographical
  The Biographical series consists of a single folder of collected material about Dingell.
  - Clippings, etc. (Box 1)
- Speeches, press releases, and interviews
  The series including Speeches, Press Releases and Interviews is ordered chronologically.
  - 1933-1955, undated; 24 folders (Box 1)
- Legislation, 1933-1955
  The Legislation series follows Dingell's apparent arrangement by subject rather than by congressional session. There are thirteen subseries in the Legislation series. For the years 1933-1936 only copies of bills--no correspondence--exist. The other twelve subseries cover the period 1936-1955. Because the contents list which follows is fairly detailed, only a few highlights of the Legislation series will receive attention here. The two most interesting and substantive subseries are "Health Insurance" and "Judges." The "Health Insurance" folders show Dingell locked in determined verbal combat with the American Medical Association. This subseries contains a large number of clippings, and the folder for 1949 contains an index to all arguments for and against the program in the Congressional Record during the 81st Congress. The "Judges" subseries contains some fairly candid assessments of the state of the Federal Circuit Courts in Michigan from the judges themselves.
  The "Personal Appeals" subseries contains some intriguing human interest stories. Most of the folders deal with persons seeking relief from deportation proceedings; the petitioners include concentration camp survivors, Polish and French war refugees, and others. The Beer Ration folder in the "Miscellaneous/Alphabetical" subseries contains a ringing defense of malt beverages by Dingell and some responses from temperance groups. The Airships folder in the same subseries describes work on behalf of a constituent manufacturing company which ended in frustration; Dingell succeeded, after much effort, in permitting the firm to enter and bid with the Navy, but the company then failed to submit a bid. The folder is also interesting in that Dingell continued to fight for dirigibles as part of U.S. air defenses well into the 1950s.
  - Miscellaneous, 1933-1936
    - General materials (Box 1)
      (no correspondence)
  - Civil Service
    - List of Unclassified Positions in: H.R. 134, 83rd Congress, 1953 (Box 1)
    - Investigation of Civil Service Commission: H.R. 22, 84th Congress, 1955 (Box 1)
    - Political Clearance of Appointments: H.R. 2117, 84th Congress, 1955-56 (Box 1)
  - Federal Employees
    - General
      - Five Day Workweek: H.R. ?, 76th Congress, 1940 (Box 1)
      - Retention of Accrued Annual Leave: H.R. 3182, 78th Congress, 1943-1944 (Box 1)
      - Pay Increase: H.R. 4075, 80th Congress, 1947 (Box 1)
      - Reimburse Uncompensated Leave to GPO Employees: H.J. Res. 175 and H.J. Res. 70, 81st and 82nd Congresses, 1949-1951 (Box 1)
      - Retirement Annuities Increase: H.R. 5874, 82nd Congress, 1952 (Box 1)
      - Unemployment Benefits: H.R. 7054, 83rd Congress, 1954 (Box 1)
      - Pay Increase: H.R. 17, 84th Congress, 1955 (Box 1)
      - Adjusted Pay Schedules: H.R. 2117, 84th Congress, 1955 (Box 1)
    - Customs
      - Promotions: H.R. 3900 and H.R. 7948, 75th Congress, 1937 (Box 1)
      - Promotions: H.R. 6811, 76th Congress, 1939-40 (Box 1)
      - Promotions: H.R. 4188, 77th Congress, 1941-1942 (Box 1)
      - Promotions and Regulation of Hours: (no legislation included), 1943-1944 (Box 1)
      - Overtime Pay: H.R. 2052 and H.R. 2643, 81st Congress, 1949 (Box 1)
      - Overtime Pay: H.R. 3550, 81st Congress, 1949-1953 (Box 1)
      - Overtime Pay: H.R. 3714 and H.R. 7767, 81st Congress, 1949-1950 (Box 1)
      - Retroactive Overtime Pay: H.R. 5194, 82nd Congress, 1949-1951 (Box 1)
      - Overtime Pay: H.R. 1006, 82nd Congress, 1951 (Box 1)
      - Retroactive Overtime Pay: H.R. 1009, 82nd Congress, 1951 (Box 1)
      - Retroactive Overtime Pay: H.R. 1714, 83rd Congress, 1953 (Box 1)
      - Retroactive Overtime Pay: H.R. 3425, 84th Congress, 1955 (Box 1)
    - Postal
      - Special Delivery Messengers: H.R. 4825 and H.R. 2528, 76th and 77th Congresses, 1937-1941 (Box 2)
        (includes three letters from President Roosevelt)
      - Pay Increase: H.R. 4704, 80th Congress, 1947-48 (Box 2)
      - Pay Increase: H.R. 17, 84th Congress, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Health Insurance Program, National
    - H.R. 2561, 78th Congress, 1943-44 (Box 2)
    - H.R. 3293 and H.R. 4730, 79th Congress, 1945 (Box 2)
    - H.R. 3548, 80th Congress, 1947 (Box 2)
    - H.R. 783, 81st Congress, 1949 (Box 2)
    - H.R. 54, 82nd Congress, 1951-52 (Box 2)
    - H.R. 1817, 83rd Congress, 1953-54 (Box 2)
    - H.R. 95, 84th Congress, 1955-56 (Box 2)
    - Press Statements and Speeches, 1944-1953 (Box 2)
    - Clippings, 1948-1955; 5 folders (Box 2)
  - Judges, Federal
    - Additional Judges for Michigan's Eastern District: H.R. 4129, H.R. 2761 and H.R. 257, 73rd-75th Congresses, 1933-1940 (Box 2)
    - Salaries: H.R. 715 and H.R. 716, 75th Congress, 1938 (Box 2)
      (includes letter from President Roosevelt)
    - Additional Judges for Michigan's Eastern District: H.R. 3 and H.R. 4, 83rd Congress, 1952-53 (Box 2)
    - Additional Judge for Michigan's Eastern District: H.R. 2578, 84th Congress, 1954-55 (Box 2)
  - Personal Appeals
    - Ajlouni, Shukri, 1951-1955 (Box 2)
    - Alverez, Antonio, 1953-1955 (Box 2)
    - Aquilina, Frank, 1952-1955 (Box 2)
    - Budzynski, Kazimierz, 1952 (Box 2)
    - Cleverly, Edward, 1949-1952 (Box 2)
    - Delimater, Edward, 1949-1950 (Box 2)
    - Drew, Chiara, 1953-1955 (Box 2)
    - Furman, Charles, 1953 (Box 2)
    - Kavanagh, Giles, 1948-1949 (Box 2)
    - Kohn, Jose, 1948-1949 (Box 2)
    - Kowalik, Olga and Jessie, 1949-1958 (Box 2)
    - Leonet, James, 1946-1947 (Box 2)
    - Miodonski, Ted, 1951-1952 (Box 2)
    - Porath, Julius, 1940 (Box 2)
    - Shafer, Itzak, 1949 (Box 2)
    - Veira, Sergio, 1953-1954 (Box 2)
    - Wojcicka, Janina, 1949-1951 (Box 2)
  - Philippines
    - Additional Cadets at U.S. Military Academies: H.R. 2281 and H.R. 2282, 75th Congress, 1937 (Box 3)
    - Elimination of Import Duties: H.R. 3142, 79th Congress, 1945 (Box 3)
    - Additional Cadets at U.S. Military Academies: H.R. 1002, 82nd Congress, 1951 (Box 3)
  - Poland
    - New U.S. Embassy: H.R. 5823 and H.R. 3377, 75th and 77th Congresses, 1937-1941 (Box 3)
    - Relief of Civilian Population: H.R. 8654, 76th Congress, 1940 (Box 3)
    - Anniversary of constitution: H.R. 493, 77th Congress, 1942 (Box 3)
  - St. Lawrence Seaway Project
    - H.J. Res. 252, 79th Congress, 1945 (Box 3)
    - H.J. Res. 271, 81st Congress, 1949 (Box 3)
    - H.J. Res. 485, 82nd Congress, 1951 (Box 3)
    - H.J. Res. 3, 82nd Congress, 1951-1952 (Box 3)
    - H.J. Res. 3, 83rd Congress, 1953 (Box 3)
    - H.J. Res. 4 and H.R. 9627, 83rd Congress, 1953-1954 (Box 3)
    - H.R. 10204, 83rd Congress, 1954 (Box 3)
    - H.R. 20 and J.R. 3894, 84th Congress, 1955 (Box 3)
  - Social Security
    - General: includes H.R. 3111 of 76th Congress, 1936-1939 (Box 3)
    - War Mobilization and Reconversion: H.R. 5227, 78th Congress, 1944 (Box 3)
    - Extension and Liberalization of Benefits: H.R. 4303, 80th Congress, 1947 (Box 3)
    - $100 Minimum: H.R. 6279, 80th Congress, 1948 (Box 3)
    - Extension and Liberalization of Benefits: H.R. 6009, 80th Congress, 1948 (Box 3)
    - Restoration of 1948 Status Quo and Repeal of Knowland Amendment: H.R. 41 and H.R. 9456, 81st Congress, 1949-50 (Box 3)
    - Repeal of Knowland Amendment: H.R. 1009, 82nd Congress, 1951 (Box 3)
    - Disability and Hospitalization Insurance: H.R. 6750 and H.R. 7484, 82nd Congress, 1952 (Box 3)
    - Extension of Benefits: H.R. 9 and H.R. 6034, 83rd Congress, 1953 (Box 3)
    - Hospitalization Insurance: H.R. 2384, 84th Congress, 1955 (Box 3)
  - Taxes
    - Excise
      - Automobiles: H.R. 3488 and H.R. 1010, 81st and 82nd Congresses, 1937-1951 (Box 3)
      - Fans: H.J. Res. 381 and H.J. Res. 69, 80th and 82nd Congresses, 1948-1953 (Box 3)
      - Wartime: H.R. 43, 81st Congress, 1949-50 (Box 3)
      - Communication Facilities; also Wartime: H.R. 6534, H.R. 1011 and H.R. 1004, 81st and 82nd Congresses, 1950-1951 (Box 3)
      - Malt Beverages; also Wildlife Sanctuaries: H.R. 6653 and H.R. 5215, 83rd Congress, 1953 (Box 3)
      - Wartime; also Admissions; others: H.R. 5, 83rd Congress, 1953 (Box 3)
      - Admissions: H.R. 6, 83rd Congress, 1953 (Box 3)
      - Coconut Oil: H.R. 9628 and H.R. 2579, 83rd and 84th Congresses, 1954-1955 (Box 3)
    - Income
      (see also Taxes, Excise, H.R. 43 and H.R. 1004; also Taxes, Other, H.R. 4968)
      - Joint Returns: H.R. 5488, 77th Congress, 1941 (Box 3)
      - Working Mothers: H.R. 7294, 83rd Congress, 1954 (Box 3)
      - Dividends and Personal Deductions: H.R. 16, 84th Congress, 1955 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous, 78th-84th Congresses, 1943-1955 (Box 3)
        (including NLRB Ordered Back Pay, Dependents' Income, Personal Exemptions, and Disabled Taxpayers)
    - Other
      - Automobiles: H.R. 2894, 75th Congress, 1937 (Box 3)
      - Losses of Spirits in Repacking: H.R. 5591, 79th Congress, 1946 (Box 3)
      - Imported Beer: H.R. 6162, 80th Congress, 1936-1948 (Box 3)
      - President's Tax Proposal: H.R. 4968, 80th Congress, 1948 (Box 3)
      - Excess Profits: H.R. 7109, 80th Congress, 1948 (Box 3)
      - Excess Profits: H.R. 42, 81st Congress, 1949-50 (Box 3)
      - Non-beverage Alcohol: H.R. 7911 and H.R. 55, 81st and 82nd Congresses, 1950-1951 (Box 3)
      - Beer Lost to Flood: H.R. 5828, H.R. 6241and H.R. 1992, 82nd and 83rd Congresses, 1951-1953 (Box 3)
      - Miscellaneous, 78th-84th Congresses, 1943-1955 (Box 3)
        (including KIA Estates, Rectifying Plants, Tax Exempt Organizations, and Tax Accountants)
  - Trade, Tariffs, and Customs Duties
    (see also Philippines and Taxes, Other)
    - Copper Tariffs: H.R. 5461, 75th Congress, 1937 (Box 3)
    - Duties on Canadian Goods: H.R. 8099, 75th Congress, 1937-1938 (Box 3)
    - Presidential Authority to Negotiate Trade Agreements: H.R. 40, 81st Congress, 1948-1949 (Box 3)
    - Free Importation of Twine: H.R. 2642 and H.R. 1005, 81st and 82nd Congresses, 1949-1951 (Box 3)
    - Plumage Tariffs: H.R. 2935, 82nd Congress, 1951-1952 (Box 3)
    - Altars and Shrines Tariffs: H.R. 6699 and H.R. 7593, 82nd Congress, 1952 (Box 3)
    - Canadian Beer and Liquor Imports: H.J. Res. 195, 84th Congress, 1955 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Alphabetical
      - Airports, National System of: H.R. 6972 and H.J. Res. 554, 75th and 76th Congresses, 1937-1940; 2 folders (Box 4)
      - Airships, Metalclad: H.R. 7715, 74th Congress, 1936-1950 (Box 4)
      - Advertisements for Alcoholic Beverages and Tobacco: H.R. 9153, 83rd Congress, 1954-1955 (Box 4)
      - Beer
        - Cans: H.R. 3321, 82nd Congress, 1951 (Box 4)
        - Soldiers' Rations: H.R. 9639, 81st Congress, 1950-1951 (Box 4)
      - Bituminous Coal: H.R. 5491, 78th Congress, 1944-1945 (Box 4)
      - Blood, National Bank System for: H.J. Res. 68, 81st Congress, 1950-1951 (Box 4)
      - Consumers' Counsel, Establishment of U.S.: H.R. 6240 and H.R. 2932, 82nd and 83rd Congresses, 1952-1953 (Box 4)
      - Defense Unemployment Compensation Act, Supplementary Compensation under: H.R. 6174, 82nd Congress, 1952 (Box 4)
      - Denaturalization and Deportation of Felons: H.R. ?, 78th Congress, 1943 (Box 4)
      - Detroit, Commemorative Stamp of: H.R. 8917, 81st Congress, 1950 (Box 4)
      - Doehler-Jarvis Corp., Relief of: H.R. 5917, 79th Congress, 1946-1947 (Box 4)
      - Federal Government Buildings, Plumbing in: H.J. Res. 254, 74th Congress, 1935-1938 (Box 4)
        (includes two President Roosevelt letters)
      - Finland, Sale of Arms to: H.R. 7726, 76th Congress, 1940 (Box 4)
      - Fort Wayne, Refurbishment of: H.R. 9995, 75th Congress, 1937-1938 (Box 4)
        (includes President Roosevelt letter)
      - Gold Star Mothers, Money for: H.R. 2759, 74th Congress, 1934-1935 (Box 4)
      - Handicapped, Federal Agency for the: H.R. 5471, 84th Congress, 1955 (Box 4)
      - Highways, Cross-country System of
        - H.R. 7, 83rd Congress, 1952-1953 (Box 4)
        - H.R. 18, 84th Congress, 1955 (Box 4)
      - Hospital Corps, Army and Navy, Discrimination Against Enlisted Men in: H.R. 5171 and H.R. 5172, 78th Congress, 1944 (Box 4)
      - Immigration
        - Amendments to Laws of: H.R. 4477, 84th Congress, 1955 (Box 4)
        - Special Quota for Polish Veterans and Axis Civilian Escapees: H.R. 5825, 83rd Congress, 1953 (Box 4)
      - Israel, Economic Aid for: H.R. 57, 82nd Congress, 1951 (Box 4)
      - Miller, Dorie, Medal of Honor for: H.R. 6800, 77th Congress, 1942 (Box 4)
      - National Labor Relations Board, Printing and Publishing Industry: H.R. 2150 and H.R. 96, 83rd and 84th Congresses, 1953; 1955 (Box 4)
      - Olympic Games 1956 for Detroit: H.J. Res. 178, 81st Congress, 1949 (Box 4)
      - Policemen and Firemen, D.C., Increased Benefits for: H.R. 56 and H.R. 2246, 82nd and 83rd Congresses, 1951-1953 (Box 4)
      - Postal Station, Roosevelt Park, Expansion of: H.R. 4869, 80th Congress, 1947-1948 (Box 4)
      - Pulaski Memorial Day, General Casimir: H.J. Res. 505, H.R. 78, and H.J. Res. 77, 75th, 77th and 78th Congresses, 1937; 1941; 1943 (Box 4)
      - Radio Day, Proclamation of National: H.J. Res 585, 76th Congress, 1940 (Box 4)
      - Securities, U.S., Disposition of: H.R. 3330, 77th Congress, 1942 (Box 4)
      - Veterans
        (see also Taxes, Other, Miscellaneous)
        - World War II, Bonus for: H.R. 2853, H.R. 4343 and H.R. 394, 78th and 79th Congresses, 1943-1947 (Box 4)
        - Korea, Unemployment Insurance for: H.R. 4526, 82nd Congress, 1952 (Box 4)
      - Zephyr Aircraft Corporation, Claims Against U.S.: H.R. 3094, 79th Congress, 1944-1946 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous
      - 1939-1949 (Box 4)
      - 1950-1955 (Box 4)